Finding Aid for Walter H. Sawyer papers, 1900-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter H. Sawyer papers
1900-1931
Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.
8684 Aa 2; Ac
Hillsdale, Michigan physician, regent of the University of Michigan. Correspondence, notes, reports, addresses, and other papers relating to board of regents activities and state medical issues.
5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Thomas Mitchell Sawyer (donor no. 433 ) and came to the library in 1936.
The collection is open to research.
Walter H. Sawyer was born August 10, 1861 in Huron County, Ohio. He graduated from the University of Michigan homeopathic medical school in 1884, then moved to Hillsdale, Michigan, where he began his practice. Also politically active, Sawyer was a member of the Republican State Central Committee from 1904 to 1908. In 1905 he was elected to the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan. He would be reelected three times. Respected as a regent, Sawyer became a member of its executive committee (from 1908) as well as its finance committee (from 1911). Because of his medical background, Sawyer was especially involved in issues relating to the administration of the hospital and the medical school.
In addition, Sawyer served as trustee of Hillsdale College from 1896 until his death. He was also active in several medical professional associations, including the Michigan State Board of Registration in Medicine, the Michigan State Medical Society, and the Detroit Academy of Medicine.
Sawyer died April 28, 1931.
The Sawyer papers contain a mixture of papers relating to his political and regental activities, and to his medical practice and association with professional medical groups. The collection has been arranged into three series: Correspondence and other papers (arranged chronologically); University of Michigan Board of Regents; and Addresses and Miscellaneous. Sawyer's regent's papers are significant for information on those individuals who were considered for the presidency of the University of Michigan in 1909, 1920, 1925, and 1930. As a heavily involved regent, Sawyer maintained communications with his fellow regents, with university presidents and other administrators. These letters and other documents will be found throughout the Correspondence series. These individuals include James B. Angell, Harry B. Hutchins, Marion L. Burton, Clarence C. Little, and Alexander Ruthven.
Subjects:
Alumni Memorial Hall (University of Michigan); Elections--Michigan--1910.; Elections--Michigan--1918.; Hillsdale (Mich.); Hillsdale College.; Medicine--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan. Board of Registration in Medicine.; Michigan State Medical Society.; Physicians--Michigan--Hillsdale.; Republican Party (Mich.); Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; University of Michigan--Sports.Sports.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Medical School.; University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.; Brooks, Stratton D. (Stratton Duluth), 1869-1949.; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934.; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939.; Finley, John H. (John Huston), 1863-1940.; Garfield, James Rudolph, 1865-1950.; Gay, Edwin F. (Edwin Francis), 1867-1946.; Gayley, Charles Mills, 1858-1932.; Hall, James Parker, 1871-1928.; Hill, Albert Ross, 1847-1909.; Hill, David Jayne, 1850-1932.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Jenks, Jeremiah Whipple, 1856-1929.; Jessup, Walter A. (Walter Albert), 1877-1944; Keppel, Frederick P. (Frederick Paul), 1875-1943.; King, Henry Churchill, 1858-1934.; Perry, Bliss, 1860-1954.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Van Tyne, Claude Halstead, 1869-1930.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hillsdale (Mich.)--Streets.; Knights Templar (Masonic order); Parades and processions.; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Streets--Michigan--Hillsdale.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Cook, William W. (William Wilson), 1858-1930.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921.; Hanchett, Benjamin Sawtell, 1868-1933.; Hunsaker, Walter Jerome, 1857-1939.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Lane, Victor Hugo, 1852-1930.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Mauck, Joseph William, 1852-1937.; May, Thomas, 1860-1927.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence and other papers
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - 1900-June 1909, 53 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1909-June 1913, 49 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1913-1923, 55 folders (Box 3)
    (include material on Chase Osborn's senatorial campaign, 1918; also on selection of a president for Hillsdale College in 1920)
  - 1924-June 1929, 27 folders (Box 4)
  - July 1929-1931, 8 folders (Box 5)
- University of Michigan Board of Regents
  - Presidential search files, 1909
    - Woodrow Wilson, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - John H. Finley (Box 5)
    - Henry C. King (Box 5)
    - James R. Garfield (Box 5)
    - Elmer E. Brown (Box 5)
    - J. Jenks (Cornell) (Box 5)
    - David J. Hill (Box 5)
    - Stratton D. Brooks (Box 5)
    - Charles E. Hughes (Box 5)
    - Edwin F. Gay (Box 5)
    - Bliss Perry (Box 5)
    - James P. Hall (Box 5)
    - Charles M. Gayley (Box 5)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Presidential search files, 1920
    - Livingston Farrand (Box 5)
    - James R. Angell, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Albert Ross Hill (Box 5)
    - Walter A. Jessup (State University of Iowa) (Box 5)
    - W.T. Foster (Box 5)
    - Henry Suzzalo (pres., University of Washington) (Box 5)
    - Frederick P. Keppel (Box 5)
    - Frank Vanderlip (Box 5)
    - Donald, J. Cowling (Box 5)
    - Marion L. Burton (Box 5)
    - General (Box 5)
  - Presidential search, 1925 (Box 5)
    (summary reports on various candidates)
  - Presidential search correspondence, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Clements, William L., correspondence with, 1919-1931; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Investigation of Undersecretary James Wade, 1908 (Box 5)
  - University Hospital Administration, 1924 (Box 5)
  - University Hospital; University physician miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Relationship of universities to schools of homeopathy, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution (A. J. Brosseau), 1928 (Box 5)
    (criticism of comments made by Clarence Cook Little and Claude Van Tyne)
  - William Cook will (with biographical sketch) (Box 5)
  - Medical School dean Hugh Cabot (Box 5)
- Addresses and miscellaneous
  - Addresses on medical subjects (Box 5)
  - Addresses to medical organization (Box 5)
  - Addresses at Hillsdale College (Box 5)
    (Good Health Week and Dedication of Mitchell Library)
  - Addresses concerning The University of Michigan (Box 5)
    (Dedication of Alumni Memorial Hall; Tribute to President James B. Angell)
  - Miscellaneous speeches and reports (Box 5)
  - Legislative acts and resolution concerning medical subjects (Box 5)
  - Legislative acts and resolution concerning The University of Michigan (Box 5)
  - Clippings and other printed materials, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    (see also certificate of election in oversize folder Ac)
  - Photographs (Box 5)